A Guide to the Louise Pearce papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA188
Rockefeller Archive Center
Louise Pearce papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
1913-1959
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Pearce, Louise, b. 1886
Flexner, Simon
FA188
1 Cubic Feet 1 box and 5 volumes
1 box 5 volumes, circa 1½ feet
Biographical/Historical note
Louise Pearce, 1885-1959 physician and medical researcher was connected with The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research from 1913 when she came as a fellow. She remained at the Institute and advanced to Associate Member from which position she retired in 1951. She was a key figure in developing the drug tryparsamide to control African sleeping sickness for which she received the King Leopold II prize of $10,000 and was made an officer of the Royal Order of the Lion. She worked closely with Dr. Wade Brown and their accomplishments included the discovery of the Brown-Pearce carcinoma a rabbit cancer and also the virus cause of rabbit pox. In 1935 she moved her laboratory to the Department of Plant and Animal Pathology at Princeton where after Dr. Brown's death she finished up the work he had started on constitution.
Additional biographical material about Louise Pearce is located in a folder in the Archives office bio file.
Biographical note
1885 Born March 5, Winchester, Massachusetts
1900-1903 Girls' Collegiate School, Los Angeles, Calif.
1907 A.B. Stanford University
1907-1909 Boston University
1912 M.D. The Johns Hopkins Medical School
1912-1913 Medical House Officer, The Johns Hopkins Hospital
1913-1914 Fellow, The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
1914-1915 Assistant, RIMR
1915-1923 Associate, RIMR
1920-1921 African sleeping sickness mission, Belgian Congo
1923-1935 Associate Member, RIMR
1931-1932 Visiting Professor of Medicine, Peiping Union Medical College, China
1935-1950 Associate Member RIMR Department Animal Pathology, Princeton
1951 Retired
1959 Died August 10, New York Hospital, New York City
Served on:
1921-1920 New York Infirmary for Women and Children (Trustee)
1925-1944 American Social Hygiene Association General Advisory Council
1931-1933 National Research Council
1940-1946 Princeton Hospital
1941- Women's Medical College, Philadelphia Member Board of Corporators (President 1946-1951)
Honorary degrees
1947 Sc. D. Wilson College
1948 Litt. D. Beaver College, Jenkintown, Pa.
1950 Sc. D. Bucknell University
1950 LL. D. Skidmore College
1952 D.M.S. Women's Medical College
Honors
1921 (?) Order of the Crown (Belgium)
1951 Elizabeth Blackwell Citation. New York Infirmary
1952 Women's Medical College Citation
1953 Leopold II Award
Officer of Royal Order of the Lion
Member of: American Medical Women's Association (Member of Executive Board), AAAS member, New York Academy of Medicine, Harvey Society, American Society for Experimental Pathology, American Association of University Women (1945-1951 Director), American Society for Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics, American Association of Pathologists and Bacteriologists, Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine, American Association for Cancer Research, New York Society of Tropical Medicine, Johns Hopkins Surgical and Medical Association, American Society of Tropical Medicine, College of Physicians of Philadelphia, Pathology Society (Great Britain and Ireland), Royal Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene, British Society for Study of Venereal Disease (honorary), Société belge de médecine tropicale (corresponding), Peiping Society of Natural History Phi Beta Kappa, Sigma Xi, Alpha Omega Alpha, Order of the Crown (Belgium — honorary), Cosmopolitan Club
Scope and Contents note
This collection consists primarily of administrative correspondence, a folder of scattered biographical material and photographs, bibliography and five volumes of Collected Reprints.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers of Louise Pearce Were deposited with the Rockefeller University Archives on her death by the administration.
Box 1, Folders 4-6 were added to the collection in June 1980 by the Rockefeller University Faculty Records Office.
Box 1, Folders 7-10 were added to the collection in February 1987 by Lila J. Magie.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 P315
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research.
Trypanosomiasis; Africa; Tumors in animals; Animals -- Diseases; Life sciences; African trypanosomiasis; Medical research; Medical education; Medical sciences; Biochemistry; Pathology; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Biology -- Research; Diseases; Rockefeller University; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Pearce, Louise, b. 1886; Flexner, Simon
- Who's Who photocopy (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Excerpt from Minutes of Board of Scientific Directors, 1947 April 19 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Newspaper clippings (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, photographs and "Extraits" du Bulletin de l'Institut Royal Colonial Belge dealing with award of Leopold II and conferring of Officer of the Royal Order of the Lion (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Copy of news article and letter from grateful patient Newspaper obituaries (Box 1, Folder 1)
- RIMR News release for obituaries (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Photographs (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1913-1931 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence dealing with application as a fellow at The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research which includes handwritten letters from Louise Pearce as well as recommendations from W.H. Howell and Lewellys F. Barker and letter concurring in appointment from Theodore Janeway. Also included is 1920-21 correspondence regarding maps prepared by the National Research Council on tropical diseases and sanitation in the African colonies.
- Reports on progress in use of tryparsamide, 1925 October 1926 October (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Letter of evaluation (handwritten) by W.H. Brown to Simon Flexner, 1929 April 21 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Administrative correspondence, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Dealing with leave of absence Mar.-Oct. 1931 to visit European Universities and plans for year, 1931-1932 at Peking Union Medical College and the work to be carried on while there.
  Includes correspondence dealing with tryparsamide supplied to certain clinics in Germany under the direction of specific clinicians.
- Correspondence and employed record of Margaret Dunham, 1932-1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Pottier, R. and van den Branden, F. Note on sujet du tryparsamide ou tryponarsyl. "Annales de la Société belge de médecine tropicale." 13 (1933)
  - Correspondence between Simon Flexner and Louise Pearce during time at Peking Union Medical College. Also includes correspondence dealing with space and budgets on return and bills for animals shipped to Institute from China, 1932 January 11-October 21
  - Correspondence regarding the rental of a house in Princeton and routine administrative correspondence dealing with budgetary arrangements and completion of Wade Brown work on constitution, 1935
  - Employed record of Margaret Dunham who returned to New York City laboratories
- Collected Reprints, 1915-1920 1921-1924 1925-1928 1929-1931 1932-1950; 5 bound volumes
- Correspondence and article, 1953-1963
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Additions to the papers by Faculty Records Office June 1980.
  - Correspondence, 1953-1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Consists mainly of correspondence with Margaret Dunham after the death of Dr. Pearce in 1959, and correspondence Dr. Paul A. Rosahn regarding an analysis of the material on malignancy which had been collected by Dr. Pearce and not evaluated at the time of her death.
  - Article, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 5, Folder 6)
    Carbon copy of the two part article left incomplete at the time of Dr. Pearce's death but which was revised enough so that it was published in JOURNAL OF EXPERIMENTAL MEDICINE, 111 (1960) 810-830.
- Simon Flexner/Pearce administrative correspondence, 1918-1929
  Addition to the collection, found in inactive files of the RU Corporate Secretary/Faculty Administrator, rec'd Feb 1987 from Lila J. Magie.
  - 1918-1923 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1924-1925 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1926-1929 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - undated (Box 1, Folder 10)